Guide to the Charles Frederick Chandler Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Charles Frederick Chandler Papers
1847-1937
[Bulk Dates: 1864-1925].
Chandler, Charles Frederick, 1836-1925.
135.25 linear feet (241 document boxes, 32 record storage cartons, 3 small flat boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
MS#0209
4078595
Chemist, Professor, and President of the New York Metropolitan Board of Health, Professor Chandler taught at Union College before joining the faculty of Columbia University where he taught in the Chemical Department, the College of Physicians and Surgeons, and served as one of the founders and long-time Dean of Columbia University's School of Mines. He was interested in Industrial Chemistry and Public Health, serving on the New York Metropolitan Board of Health for many years and implementing a number of significant public health and public housing reforms.
Biographical Note
Charles Frederick Chandler was an important American chemist and chemical educator. He was deeply involved in issues of chemistry, mining, and public health throughout the last third of the nineteenth and early decades of the twentieth centuries. As a professor at Columbia University, he revolutionized chemical education in the United States and was a major proponent of practical, scientific education. He was deeply involved in professional organizations and kept scrupulously abreast of scientific advancements, keeping detailed notes and files of clippings and articles about different chemical and scientific matters. He often acted as an expert witness in legal cases dealing with chemical matters and was well respected as an expert in his field.
Chandler was born in Lancaster, Massachusetts on December 6, 1836. His family moved shortly after his birth to New Bedford, Massachusetts, where he spent most of his formative years and engaged in his earliest formal education. As a child he devoted nearly all of his free time to scientific and geological explorations and attending public lectures on scientific subjects. These public lectures at the New Bedford Lyceum, in particular a series of lectures given by the geologist and naturalist Louis Agassiz, sparked his lifelong interest in science. He was particularly interested in mineralogy and collected rock and mineral samples that he found around his grandfather's Lancaster home.
Upon completion of his studies at New Bedford High School, Chandler spent a year in private study, learning Latin and Greek and conducting chemical experiments in a laboratory he set up in his father's attic to prepare himself for more advanced chemical study. He then left his home in New Bedford and enrolled in the Lawrence Scientific School of Harvard University. While at Harvard he studied Industrial Chemistry, but he was encouraged to continue his studies in Industrial Chemistry and Geology in Germany, which was at the forefront of scientific education at the time. He enrolled in the University of Göttingen in 1854 to study with Friedrich Woehler, and after studying under Woehler and working as an assistant in the lad of Heinrich Rose, the father of analytic chemistry, he earned his Ph.D. from the University of Göttingen in 1856.
After completing his degree, Chandler returned to the United States to pursue his own scientific career. Upon his return, in 1857, Chandler became the chemical assistant at Professor Charles Joy's laboratory at Union College in Schenectady, New York and shortly thereafter began to lecture on Mineralogy and Geology at the College as well as manage the laboratory. He became an associate professor at the College in 1857 at the age of 21. He remained at Union College for the next 7 years during which time he ran the chemistry lab and married his first wife, Anna Craig Chandler.
His tenure at Union College ended in 1864 when Chandler was asked by his former colleague, Professor Joy, to consider taking on the Chair of Chemistry at the newly formed Columbia University School of Mines that Professor Thomas Egleston and General Vinton were attempting to start under President Barnard. Chandler took the opportunity to move to New York, and begin his long relationship with Columbia University.
The School of Mines, later to develop into the School of Engineering and Applied Science, consisted at this time of one room in the basement of a Madison Avenue academic building. Within the first year of the School's existence, Chandler took on the position of Dean, and under his leadership in that first year the school moved to a larger four floor building and doubled the number of students enrolled in its program of study. Chandler was to remain dean of the School of Mines for the next 33 years, through its move to its new home on Columbia's Morningside Campus and into Havermeyer Hall, the state-of-the-art Chemistry building that he helped to design.
Though he stepped down as the Dean of the School of Mines in 1897, he continued to teach chemistry at Columbia University until 1910, where students described him as an extremely popular and engaging instructor.
Though Chandler is perhaps most associated with the School of Mines, he also, starting in 1867, began lecturing in Chemistry for the New York College of Pharmacy. He acted as president of this school until 1897 when it formalized its relationship to Columbia University and was incorporated as a University Faculty in 1897. He also lectured in Columbia's College of Physicians and Surgeons in 1872 where he taught chemistry and medical jurisprudence and called for a more rigorous scientific training for medical professionals. In addition to his instructional and administrative duties, Chandler also started a Chemical Museum, later named the Chandler Chemical Museum in his honor, to highlight the accomplishments of modern industrial and analytic chemistry.
While Chandler was a very popular instructor, he was not always so popular among his colleagues. He spent much of his time acting as an expert witness in various legal cases and patent disputes, and performed independent consulting work for companies such as Standard Oil. Many of Chandler's colleagues had concerns that Chandler was more focused on his profitable, outside consulting work than he was on his academic and administrative duties.
Though he was not entirely without controversy, Chandler remained an integral part chemical education at Columbia University until 1911 when he finally, after 46 years of service at Columbia and 54 years of college teaching, retired. Upon retirement he and his second wife, Augusta Berard Chandler, continued to reside in New York City, but spent more and more time at their summer home in Westhampton and at her family's home in New Hartford, Connecticut, where Chandler died in 1825.
While chemical instruction made up much of Charles Chandler's career, he was also an energetic public health advocate and sanitation reformer. His career in public service began in 1866 when the Secretary of the Metropolitan Board of Health asked Chandler to perform some chemical work for the board, ex officio. The Board soon realized the value of having a chemist as part of the organization and later that year Chandler was appointed as chemist to the Board of Health. In 1873 Mayor Havermeyer appointed Chandler to the Presidency of the Metropolitan Board of Health, a position he held until 1883.
His work with the New York City Municipal Board of Health led to a number of important sanitary reforms in the city. When he began his services on the Board of Health in 1866, 53 out of every 100 deaths in the city were children under the age of 5. He implemented major reforms to improve infant nutrition, including stopping the sale of watered-down milk, and instituted a corps of traveling physicians to tend to the residents of tenements. By the time he left the Board, the child mortality rate had fallen to 46 out of every 100 deaths, an estimated saving of 8000 lives and 5000 children per annum. He was a strong advocate for tenement reform, designing tenement houses that were cleaner and brighter than those most prevalent in the City, and pushing a "Tenement House Act" through legislature. This is all in addition to the more mundane tasks of testing household goods such as cosmetics, patent medicine, and wallpaper for toxic and potentially harmful additives. The Board of Health, under his leadership is credited with preventing a cholera epidemic in 1883. He, himself, thought his most important work with the Board of Health was his work in reducing fatal kerosene related accidents through informing the public about the dangers of kerosene with naphtha and gasoline added (making combustible vapors). All in all, Chandler's leadership of the Board of Health marks an important chapter in the history of sanitation in New York.
Chandler was very active in professional and social organizations, belonging to several Chemical Clubs and Organizations. While some of his clubs were purely or primarily social, other such as The Chemists' Club, which Chandler founded, were intended to build professional connections among scientists in New York. He also founded the American Chemical Society, and served twice as its president, first in 1881 and again in 1889, and served as the president of the Society of Chemical Industry. In 1870 he and his brother William Henry Chandler, a Chemistry Professor at Lehigh University, started the journal The American Chemist, the first chemical journal in The United States.
He received a number of honorary degrees, the Gold Medal of the National Institute of Social Sciences, and the prestigious Perkin Medal from the Society of Chemical Industry. After he retired from Columbia University, the alumni of that University set up an endowment for the Chandler lectureship and the Chandler medal in his honor.
Scope and Content
Chemist, Professor, and President of the New York Metropolitan Board of Health. Professor Chandler taught at Union College before joining the faculty of Columbia University where he taught in the Chemical Department, the College of Physicians and Surgeons, and served as one of the founders and long-time Dean of Columbia University's School of Mines. He was interested in Industrial Chemistry and Public Health, serving on the New York Metropolitan Board of Health for many years and implementing a number of significant public health and public housing reforms.
This collection consists of material related to Charles F. Chandler's long career with Columbia University, as well as other professional activities, personal and household affairs, and his extensive collection of subject files on chemistry and general scientific matters. Within the Charles Frederick Chandler Papers there are letters, photographs, scrapbooks, ledgers, lab analyses, and some publications, including trade publications and price lists.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 3 series:
Series I: Personal, 1847-1925
Subseries I.1: Correspondence, 1857-1925
Subseries I.2: Biographical Material, 1847-1925
Subseries I.3: Financial Records, 1825-1926
Subseries I.4: Photographs, Undated
Series II: Professional, 1864-1937
Subseries II.1: Awards and Honors, 1904-1937
Subseries II.2: Academic and Scholarly Activities, 1864-1925
Subseries II.3: Municipal Board of Health, 1868-1888
Series III. Subject Files, Undated.
Subjects
Chandler, Charles Frederick, 1836-1925.; Chemists' Club (New York, N.Y.); Columbia University.--College of Pharmacy--History.; Columbia University.--College of Physicians and Surgeons.; Columbia University.--Dept. of Chemistry.; Columbia University--History.; Columbia University.--School of Mines.; Chemistry--History--19th century.; Chemistry--Industrial applications.; Chemistry--Research.; Chemistry--Study and teaching.; Dye industry--United States--History.; Dyes and dyeing.; Photography--Processing.; Photography--Research.; Photographic chemistry.; Public health--New York (State)--New York.; Advertisements.; Aniline Dyes.; Arsenic.; Black-and-white photographs.; Blueprints (reprographic copies).; Brochures.; Cartes-de-visite (card photographs).; Charts.; Cloth.; Cyanotypes.; Dye.; Graphs.; Photoprints.; Printing plates.; Receipts (financial records).; Scrapbooks.; Wallpapers.; Chemists.; College teachers.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
1937 M-37 Gift
1940 M-40 Epstean, Edward Gift
The material in the information file was salvaged when Professor Chandler's former home was demolished in 1937. Gift in 1937; gift of Edward Epstean, 1940.
Related Material- At Columbia
Central Files Records, 1890-1971 Columbia University Archives, Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Columbia University
Charles Frederick Chandler architectural records and papers collection Avery Architecture and Fine Arts Library, Columbia University
Historical Photograph Collection Columbia University Archives, Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Columbia University
- Series I: Personal, 1847-1925
  The Personal Series is comprised of material related to Chandler's personal and domestic life, including material relating to the upkeep and management of his home and a number of photographs of Chandler and his associates. Additionally, the series contains his correspondence files relating to matters both personal and professional.
  - Subseries I.1: Correspondence, 1857-1925
    Subseries I.1 contains correspondence both sent and received by Charles Chandler. Though this file falls within the series of Chandler's personal papers, this correspondence often relates to his professional life and could have been sent in any of his various capacities as professor, member of the Metropolitan Board of Health, and a member of various professional organizations. The subseries also includes the correspondence of Chandler's second wife, Augusta Chandler and correspondence relating to their wedding.
    - A-Z, (20 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 1 to 20)
    - 1860-1925, (4 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 24 to 27)
    - 1860-1925, (7 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 1 to 7)
    - 1870-1924 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Personal, 1870-1924 (Box 3, Folder 2 to 3)
    - Chandler, Augusta Mrs., 1904-1928 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Christmas Cards, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Kimball, 1891-1918 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Marriage to Ms. Augusta Polhemus, 1905 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Letterbooks, 1857-1891, (3 volumes) (Box 4, Folder 1 to 3)
  - Subseries I.2: Biographical Materials, 1847-1925
    This subseries contains a great deal of information related to Chandler's personal life and professional activities including some biographical articles and printed matter about Chandler, the subject files related to his many professional and social clubs and organizations, as well as school work and early diaries and scrapbooks depicting his younger life and travels. This series also includes the realia and three dimensional material connected with the collection but not part of one of Chandler's specific subject files. The objects in this series range from Chandler's pipe to small chemical apparatus. Also of interest here are some of Mrs. Augusta Chandler's files, notably scrapbooks such as her dinner party or opera-going books which depict the social obligations of a well-to-do woman in New York at the turn of the twentieth century.
    - Artifacts (Box 5)
    - Address Books, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Biographical Materials (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Biographical-- Printed, 1883-1944 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Card Plates (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Consultant Fees (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Clippings-- General, (6 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 1 to 6)
    - Clubs and Societies, 1870-1924
      - A, (5 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 1 to 5)
      - A-I, (6 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 1 to 6)
      - K-N, (6 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 1 to 6)
      - O-S, (7 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 1 to 7)
      - S- W, (6 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 1 to 6)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Payments and Dues, (2 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 2 to 3)
    - Course Work
      - Harvard
        - Class Notes, 1953-1954 (Box 14, Folder 1)
        - Journals and Class Notes, 1953-1954 (Box 14, Folder 2)
      - Secondary School
        - Notes and Assignments (Box 14, Folder 3)
      - University of Göttingen
        - 1855-1856 (Box 14, Folder 4)
        - Class Notes, 1855-1856, (2 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 5)
        - Correspondence, 1855-1902 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Diaries, 1876-1893 (scattered) (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Family History (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Notebooks, Undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Scrapbook, 1847-1855 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Trip to Europe, 1869 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Will and Legal Documents (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Scrapbooks
      - 1882-1886 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Food and Drug Fraud Clippings, 1868-1869 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Trip to Europe, 1896 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Chandler, Augusta Mrs. Material
      - Correspondence with Charles Chandler, 1904 and undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Calendar, 1925 (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - Notebooks (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - Scrapbooks
        - General, 1904 and 1914-1915, (2 Folders) (Box 17, Folder 4 to 5)
        - Addresses (Box 17, Folder 6)
        - Dinner Parties, 1909-1911 (Box 18, Folder 1)
        - Recipes, 1908-1909 and Undated, (3 Folders) (Box 18, Folder 2 to 4)
        - Opera, 1908 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Subseries I.3: Financial Records, 1825-1926
    These files provide an intimate glimpse into the Chandler household through detailed information about household accounts, including bills, receipts and correspondence about standing orders and accounts. Additionally, the subseries includes information about many properties either owned or managed by Charles and Augusta Chandler, many of which were ancestral properties that were willed to the couple. Copies of some of these wills and property deeds are included.
    - Account Books, 1855-1921 (7 Boxes) (Box 19-25)
    - Household Accounts
      - Bills and Receipts, 1902-1920, (2 Folders) (Box 26, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Correspondence, 1880-1922, (2 Folders) (Box 26, Folder 3 to 4)
      - Ledgers, Undated (Box 26, Folder 5)
      - 54th St. and Madison Protection Society, 1890-1907 (Box 26, Folder 6)
      - Middle Park Ave. Improvement Association, 1902 (Box 26, Folder 7)
      - Westhampton House, 1880-1891, (2 Folders) (Box 27, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Westhampton House-- Plans and Drawings (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Properties and Estates
      - Craig Family Estates
        - General, 5 Folders (Box 28, Folder 1 to 5)
        - Correspondence, 1868-1879, (4 Folders) (Box 29, Folder 1 to 4)
        - Deeds, (2 Folders) (Box 29, Folder 5 to 6)
        - Legal Documents 1825-1883, (6 Folders) (Box 30)
      - Berard Estates, 1890-1924, (2 Folders) (Box 31, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Hudson Estates, 1887-1891 (Box 31, Folder 3)
      - Smith Family Estates, 1913-1926, (3 Folders) (Box 31, Folder 4 to 6)
      - Miscellaneous, 1864-1925 (Box 31, Folder 7)
      - Ledger (Box 31, Folder 8)
      - Ledgers and Letterbooks, 1895-1898 and undated (Box 32)
  - Subseries I.4: Photographs, Undated
    These photographs document both, in their subject matter, Chandler's leisure activities and homes, and, in their techniques, his active interest in photographic technology. The snapshots of Chandler and his family focus on photographs of his homes and gardens and travels. In addition to these files, there are also a number of professional portraits of Chandler and his colleagues located within these files.
    - Awards (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Family Photographs, (3 Folders) (Box 33, Folder 2 to 5)
    - Houses and Gardens (Box 33, Folder 6)
    - Houses and Gardens, (6 Folders) (Box 34)
    - Laboratory and Apparatus (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Machinery (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - Negatives (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - Portraits
      - Chandler, (2 Folders) (Box 35, Folder 5 to 6)
      - Chandler, (2 Folders) (Box 36, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Chandler With Colleagues (Box 36, Folder 3)
      - Chandler's Associates, (3 Folders) (Box 36, Folder 4 to 6)
      - Cartes-de-visite (Box 36, Folder 7)
      - Chandler's German Professors (Box 36, Folder 8)
      - Female Family and Friends (Unidentified), (2 Folders) (Box 37, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Projects and Photographic Experiments (Box 37, Folder 3)
    - Professional Organizations (Box 37, Folder 4)
    - School of Mines (Box 37, Folder 5)
    - Travels
      - Art (Box 37, Folder 6)
      - England (Henley Regatta) (Box 37, Folder 7)
      - France (Box 37, Folder 8)
      - Germany (Box 37, Folder 9)
      - Italy (Box 37, Folder 10)
      - Morocco (Box 37, Folder 11)
      - Spain (Box 37, Folder 12)
      - United States (Box 37, Folder 13)
      - Unidentified (Box 37, Folder 14)
- Series II: Professional, 1864-1937
  The professional series contains files related to Chandler's professional life as a scientist and educator, and his role as a public servant on the New York Municipal Board of Health.
  - Subseries II.1: Awards and Honors, 1904-1937
    This subseries documents professional awards and honors awarded to Chandler, as well as some files related to awards he presented or otherwise helped to administer. Notably, this subseries contains files related to the Perkin medal, which was both received and presented by Chandler on different occasions, and a number of remembrances of Chandler given on the occasion of his retirement from Columbia.
    - Biographical Sketches (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - Bust, 1910 (Box 38, Folder 2)
      Material related to the commissioning of a bust of Charles Chandler
    - Chandler Centennial
      - Correspondence, 1937, (4 Folders) (Box 38, Folder 3 to 6)
      - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 39, Folder 1)
      - Clippings and Memorabilia, 1937 (Box 39, Folder 2)
    - Chandler Lecture and Foundation, 1910 and 1924 (Box 39, Folder 3)
    - Chandler Medal (Box 39, Folder 4)
    - Clippings (Box 39, Folder 5)
    - Columbia University Retirement
      - Banquets, 1910-1914, (3 Folders) (Box 39, Folder 6 to 8)
      - Clippings, 1909-1911, (3 Folders) (Box 40, Folder 1 to 3)
      - Correspondence, 1909-1910, (2 Folders) (Box 40, Folder 4 to 5)
      - Final Lecture, 1910 (Box 40, Folder 6)
      - Trustees' Statement on Chandler's Retirement, 1911 (Box 40, Folder 7)
    - Gold Medal of the National Institute of Social Sciences, 1921 (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - National Academy of Sciences Biography, 1926 (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - Perkin Medal, 1920 (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - Perkin Medal Presentations, 1906-1924, (2 Folders) (Box 41, Folder 4 to 5)
    - Portrait Commission, 1904-1910, (2 Folders) (Box 41, Folder 6 to 7)
  - Subseries II.2: Academic and Scholarly Activities, 1864-1925
    The Academic and Scholarly Activities subseries documents Chandler's teaching and administrative activities, primarily with Columbia University as well as his professional chemical and scientific activities. The Columbia files include correspondence and memos relating to his roles as teacher and administrator in a number of departments and schools, most notably as the dean of the School of Mines. Also represented in this subseries are laboratory analyses that Chandler made or oversaw in his laboratory, and files relating to the founding of The American Chemist.
    - The American Chemist
      - Correspondence, 1870-1878 (Box 42, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence (letterbook), 1871-1879 (Box 42, Folder 2)
      - Ledger, 1871-1877, (2 volumes) (Box 42, Folder 3 to 4)
    - Chemical Foundation (Box 42, Folder 5)
    - Columbia University
      - 1893-1925 (Box 42)
      - Chemical Department
        - General (Box 43, Folder 1)